Maximilian, Emperor of Mexico collection 1847-1967 (bulk 1853-1867)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
- Series IV: Articles, Ephemera, Photographs, and Broadsides, 1855-1967
  - Broadside (Zaragoza, i.e. Puebla). April 29, 1867 (Box 3)
    "A decision of the General in Chief of the Army of the East entrusts to General Juan N. Mendez the government of the State which until today has been in my charge. I return, then, to private life, after having given to my State my best services, and I return with the conviction that I have fulfilled the trust that the acceptance of the command imposed on me, in moments most critical for my country. Before retiring from public life, I should have liked to give an accounting to the people of all the acts of my administration, but circumstances did not permit"
    Garcia, however, will prepare a manifesto covering the two periods of his administration. It will be based on official records and important data, and will become the historic document of the administration of the State during his rule.
  - Broadside (Mexico). May 1, 1867 (Box 3)
    An imperial decree, signed by Marquez, which reduces from 25 percent to 20 percent of the total tax on industry and business transactions, the said 20 percent to be used to defray the expense of work involved in providing drainage in the capital city and valley of Mexico.
  - Broadside (Puebla). May 3, 1867 (Box 3)
    Program for the ceremony of the 5th of May. Eleven articles are given concerning the festivities -- bell ringing, participants, details of ceremony, fireworks, etc.
  - Broadside (Queretaro). May 19, 1867 (Box 3)
    Traitors taken prisoner at Queretaro. A list, including the Emperor and officers. Also an item referring to a message from Maximilian to Prussian Minister in Mexico requesting help in his defense.
  - Broadside (Zaragoza, i.e. Puebla). May 23, 1867 (Box 3)
    Juan N. Mendez, Brigadier General, and Civil and Military Governor of the State of Puebla, decrees that a tax shall be imposed one time only on the Catholic clergy. It shall be collected at two different dates at 10 days and 20 days from the publication of this decree. Quotas given, places named, curates of the different classes are defined. The Government reserves the right to lessen this contribution in the case of individuals who have rendered services to the cause of the Republic. The money derived from this collection will go for the General Commissary of the Army of the East and for military hospitals.
  - Broadside (Queretaro?) June 19, 1867 (Box 3)
    Last letter of Maximilian to the inhabitants of Mexico. Also last words before his execution.
  - Broadside (Puebla). June 20, 1867 (Box 3)
    Execution of Justice. Publication of the results of the trial of Maximilian, Miramon, and Mejia, who were found guilty and sentenced to death by a firing squad on June 19,1867.
  - Broadside (Zaragoza, i.e., Puebla). June 21, 1867 (Box 3)
    Viva Mexico. General Headquarters in Puebla publishes a telegram telling of the capitulation of Mexico City and steps taken to maintain public order.
  - Broadside (Zaragoza, i.e. Puebla). August 27, 1867 (Box 3)
    Juan N. Mendez, Brigadier General, and Civil and Military Governor of the State of Puebla, informs the inhabitants that the following decree of Benito Juarez, Constitutional President of the United States of Mexico, has reached him. The decree concerns the condemning adjudication, redemption or collection on property administered by the clergy.
  - Broadside (Toluca). June 1, 1895 (Box 3)
    A protest signed by students... "We protest in the most energetic way against allowing the greatest, the bloodiest, and most repugnant traitor, Leonardo Marques, to remain in the country of the martyrs of Tacubaya, and of Melchor Ocampa, innocent victims among many others of that ferocious monster... The land in whose bosom lie the sacred of Juarez, Ocampo, Gonzalez Ortega, Leandro Valle, Lerdo and a thousand others should not hold the body of that coward." Signed by Raul Lalanne and 125 others.
  - Ten Imperial Appointments and Awards, signed by Maximilian. 1864-1866 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, chiefly from Vienna and Mexico. (In German, English, and Spanish). 1867-1967 (Box 3)